<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Thibaut Courouble</title>
  <id>https://thibaut.me/</id>
  <link href="https://thibaut.me/" type="text/html" rel="alternate"/>
  <link href="https://thibaut.me/feed.xml" type="application/atom+xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2010-10-27T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thibaut Courouble</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/choose-responsibly/</id>
    <title>Choose Responsibly</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/choose-responsibly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-10-27T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Certainly one of our greatest powers is our ability to determine ourselves and
decide of our attitude at any given moment. Though this freedom finds its
limits in the conditions in which we live in, we are always free to take a
stand and even in the direst situations, to decide what to make of our
existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How we use this freedom defines who we are and, as with every great power,
&lt;a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Stan_Lee"&gt;there must also come great responsibility&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Freedom is only part of the story and half the truth. Freedom is but the
negative aspect of the whole phenomenon whose positive aspect is
responsibleness. In fact, freedom is in danger of degenerating into mere
arbitrariness unless it is lived in terms of responsibleness.
&lt;small&gt;Viktor E. Frankl&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom allows for both good and evil. While our society tries to enforce that
nobody falls to the dark side, it remains our responsibility to choose between
the many different shades of good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, this new age of science and technology has expanded our choice
and revealed to us the full scope of our freedom. While our ancestors could
rely on traditions, such as religions, to tell them what they ought to do, we
now stand fully aware of the infinite different ways in which we could live
our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that human beings, surely the most intelligent life form on earth,
do not strive to achieve their maximum potential? The reason is simple: we
have been given the freedom of choice.
&lt;small&gt;Jim Rohn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In facing a choice, multiplying the options doesn&amp;rsquo;t always lead to a better
outcome, for it then requires that we make up our mind and be strong enough to
act. In particular, the former requires a certain level of knowledge that
grows exponentially with the number of options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of life, some options are attractive at first sight but
disappointing in reality, while others take great courage to choose but offer
immense rewards in the end. Most important, some are unknown to us until we
acquire the knowledge that will reveal them to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why I find acquiring knowledge to be one of the most important
pastimes, because it broadens my view and understanding of the world, thus
increasing my opportunities and improving my judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have a remarkable potential and we must decide what to make of it.
While some might be satisfied with less than others, many strive for more.
Whatever we decide, we should not forget that everything is possible, so long
as we believe, and put in the mental effort to become what we ought to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is our responsibility to choose what&amp;rsquo;s best for us, our loved ones, and
the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/imagination/</id>
    <title>The Power of Imagination</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/imagination/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-09-19T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2010-09-19T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Imagination is one of our most precious faculties. In addition to &amp;ldquo;providing
meaning to experience, understanding to knowledge, and playing a key role in
the learning process&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imagination"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;),
imagination gives us the faculty to see the world and ourselves beyond the
present moment. Combined with the freedom of choice it makes us the master of
our fate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagination has been the seedling of all human progress but it&amp;rsquo;s also the
motive power of our individual lives. The more we use it, combined with a
burning desire for its actualization and a definite purpose, the greater our
achievements will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With experience and intelligence, imagination becomes creativity (the ability
to create new valuable things), which can then be transformed into all kinds
of riches. It&amp;rsquo;s not an easy step, but we&amp;rsquo;re all capable of achieving it —
unless we surrender to the manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our obsession with creating maps and manuals for how to live our lives goes
against the human nature, for there is no limit to what we can achieve and
become. Maps, in this sense, are counter-productive because they set
boundaries where none existed before. They help avoid the mental effort of
finding a path but offer no surprise as to what the destination will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of an infinite sea of choices, it&amp;rsquo;s natural to put blinders on, to
ask for a map, to beg for instructions, or failing that, to do exactly what
you did last time, even if it didn&amp;rsquo;t work.
&lt;small&gt;Seth Godin&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life offers an infinite sea of choices. In this frightening journey,
imagination is our own personal navigation tool. It&amp;rsquo;s always with us but we
must deliberately and repeatedly choose to use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s world of factories has created countless manuals and mapped a vast
number of paths which are followed by many. Our education system reinforces
this by making us believe that the only way for us to succeed is to follow
those paths and rules. They offer a quick and easy fix to a broader problem
that&amp;rsquo;s the meaning of one&amp;rsquo;s life, but don&amp;rsquo;t come free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While following a map can offer a temporary remedy to some of our fears, it
can only take us where someone else wishes for us to go, usually for his or
her personal benefit. Moreover, if we aren&amp;rsquo;t prepared to work without a map
and be wrong, we can&amp;rsquo;t let free of our creativity and achieve our full
potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, following our imagination won&amp;rsquo;t give us the comfort of knowing
what to do and where to go at any given moment, but its rewards are invaluable
compared to the wages that we can expect by working at the office. Beyond
success, it&amp;rsquo;ll bring us happiness and fulfillment, for we will be in charge of
our own future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man&amp;rsquo;s only limitation, within reason, lies in his development and use of his
imagination.
&lt;small&gt;Napoleon Hill&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within the laws of physics, the power of our imagination is simply limitless.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/linchpin-review/</id>
    <title>Book Review: Linchpin: Are You Indispensable?</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/linchpin-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-09-12T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2010-09-12T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Linchpin-Are-Indispensable-Seth-Godin/dp/1591843162/"&gt;Linchpin: Are You Indispensable?&lt;/a&gt;
is an excellent book by Seth Godin that explains how and why you should become
a linchpin — someone not easily replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the marketplace, the easier people are to replace the less they need to be
paid and the easier they are to lay off. The industrial revolution has created
a world of factories and factory workers which goes against the creative and
independent nature of human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, artists are now rewarded far more than they used to be. The
new age of technology makes it possible for everyone to be both remarkable and
remarked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artists are people who give more than they receive, drive change, and make
things happen. They prevent organizations from falling into pieces because
they do their best — more than what they&amp;rsquo;re paid for. They&amp;rsquo;re the ones who
keep the marketplace running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an artist in every one of us but in this factory world we&amp;rsquo;re being
taught to follow the crowd instead of striving for our own, unique path. For
millenniums men have been in charge of their own lives. Nowadays we&amp;rsquo;re being
brainwashed into thinking that the only way for us to succeed is to fit in the
system and do what others think we should be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I especially agree with Seth when he blames our education system for this
brainwashing. Schools are on the front line of our education and yet they
teach us to comply with a set of rules and live only within these limits.
They stigmatize mistakes thus preventing the expression of creativity, an
essential skill of artists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essential thing measured by school is whether or not you are good at
school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But creativity, imagination, and the freedom of choice are all part of the
human condition. They&amp;rsquo;re always available for us to use and can&amp;rsquo;t be coerced
into retreat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the resistance sits in our own mind. Fear is the greatest barrier
against becoming an artist: fear of failure, fear of working without a map,
fear of criticism… They can all be overcome by finding purpose in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The linchpin feels the fear, acknowledges it, then proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Seth puts it, &amp;ldquo;every day is a new chance to choose.&amp;rdquo; Becoming a linchpin is
certainly the best choice you could make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it that human beings, surely the most intelligent life form on earth,
do not strive to achieve their maximum potential? The reason is simple: we
have been given the freedom of choice.
&lt;small&gt;Jim Rohn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/business-execution/</id>
    <title>Business Execution</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/business-execution/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-07-30T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2010-07-30T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The idea that business ideas are worthless unless executed and execution is
worth millions has always been at the heart of my business philosophy, but
it&amp;rsquo;s only recently that I gripped the full meaning of the verb &lt;em&gt;to execute&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years I&amp;rsquo;ve believed that &lt;em&gt;to execute&lt;/em&gt; is like &lt;em&gt;to build&lt;/em&gt;. I focused too
much on the details and lost sight of the essential, that good execution is
about having good judgment — making the right decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build something requires mainly technical skills. The better our skills
are, the better our creations will be. However in the business world, if our
creations aren&amp;rsquo;t something people are willing to pay for, they&amp;rsquo;re worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While technical skills can be acquired rather easily and in a relatively short
period of time, the skill of great judgment takes time and experience to
acquire, which makes it much more valuable. It is, by and large, the
difference between an employee and his manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing the right things is more important than doing things right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote (attributed to various sources) says it all: &lt;strong&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not enough to do
it right, you have to do what&amp;rsquo;s right&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/think-and-grow-rich-review/</id>
    <title>Book Review: Think and Grow Rich</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/think-and-grow-rich-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-05-13T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2010-05-13T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Think-Grow-Rich-Original-Classic/dp/1906465592/"&gt;Think and Grow Rich&lt;/a&gt;
is a book written by Napoleon Hill first published in 1937. The book offers a
comprehensive &amp;ldquo;formula&amp;rdquo; for personal achievement which could mark a turning
point in anyone&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill spent more than two decades interviewing and synthesizing the experience
and insights of over five hundred people who achieved great wealth during
their lifetimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energetic, the book is an easy read filled with practical advice. Although
some passages may feel outdated from a scientific point of view (the world has
since made tremendous progress in the field of cognitive science), the text is
remarkably relevant for our time — a time of unprecedented opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success comes to those who are success conscious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some worry about origin, education, or amount of capital, Hill&amp;rsquo;s central
idea is that the source of wealth is non-material. Successful men and women
were not born this way, they &lt;em&gt;thought&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;grew&lt;/em&gt; rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both poverty and riches are the offspring of thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He describes 13 principles that make for the perfect personal philosophy. In
my opinion, mastering the first two, Desire and Faith, is both essential and
enough, because they will make us do whatever it takes to achieve anything we
want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success is neither magical or mysterious. Success is the natural consequence
of consistently applying the basic fundamentals.
&lt;small&gt;Jim Rohn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think and Grow Rich is a list of fundamentals that will change the way you
think and, as an extra, make you rich.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/desire/</id>
    <title>Desire</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/desire/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-03-18T20:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2010-03-18T20:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing Tennis since I was six years old. My coach and parents often
said to me: &amp;ldquo;the one who desires the victory the most will win&amp;rdquo;. This has been
one of the most fundamental lessons I&amp;rsquo;ve ever been taught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Desire is fundamental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don&amp;rsquo;t desire to live, we die.&lt;br&gt;
If we don&amp;rsquo;t desire to win, we lose.&lt;br&gt;
If we don&amp;rsquo;t desire to succeed, we fail.&lt;br&gt;
If we don&amp;rsquo;t desire anything, we get nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can only move forward if we know where we want to go, otherwise we
surrender to luck and circumstances. Lack of desire is one of the major causes
of failure, but it&amp;rsquo;s also one that&amp;rsquo;s most easily fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that having a burning, insatiable desire for something (or someone)
is the most powerful force of all. It can drive anybody to the top of any
ladder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we must be careful not to mistake wishes for desires. Wishes are empty. We
all wish for happiness and yet many of us fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishes are little more than self-delusion.
&lt;small&gt;Jim Rohn&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A devastating principle that young students often mistakenly learn from school
is that success (our personal achievements) is a function of our intelligence
(or how &amp;ldquo;gifted&amp;rdquo; we are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smartest students usually get the best marks — that&amp;rsquo;s what we see when
we&amp;rsquo;re schoolboys or schoolgirls. If you&amp;rsquo;re not smart, you&amp;rsquo;re meant to stay
behind, so you&amp;rsquo;d better put off your dreams. This can have dramatic
consequences because when there is no dreaming, there is no desire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;usually&amp;rdquo; is crucial here because it highlights the fact that this isn&amp;rsquo;t a
rule but merely an observation, and a bad one. The rule is this: the students
most willing to learn and work hard always get the best marks. Intelligence
might give you a head-start but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work by itself. No matter how far
behind you start, you can always catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our only limitations are those we set up in our own minds.
&lt;small&gt;Napoleon Hill&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success moves toward those who search for progress but the search isn&amp;rsquo;t as
easy as Google. It&amp;rsquo;s more like a treasure hunt: hard, on a rocky road strewn
with pitfalls and traps, often discouraging to the point where quitting feels
like the only option. But even in these difficult moments, if the promise of
the future is clear, the hunter won&amp;rsquo;t quit and the treasure will reveal itsef
to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common characteristic of all successful men and women is that they kept on
going. How can we do that when everything that&amp;rsquo;s around us seems to work
against us? By having a burning desire for being the one in our dreams,
because that will make us do whatever it takes to make our dreams happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The moment we start believing in our dreams is the moment they come true.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/school/</id>
    <title>School</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/school/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-02-27T19:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2010-02-27T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As time goes by I realize the importance of self-education and how valuable it
is to have the passion to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t achieve my full potential in school but feel like if I ever do it in
life, it would be because of the way I &amp;ldquo;self-learned&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have the credentials that major schools offer, but in those
disciplines I&amp;rsquo;m most passionate about — the ones that matter, I have not only
the skills but also the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students shouldn&amp;rsquo;t wait to be unemployed or &amp;ldquo;bad-employed&amp;rdquo; to start learning
the practical skills and acquiring the experience that can get them the job
they truly want. Real experience beats any credential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a diploma tells our employer what we supposedly can do, a business or
professional experience tells him what we&amp;rsquo;ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all know that rehearsing something is far different from doing it for real.
I believe the marketplace is where this rule is the most strictly applied. The
closer we grow to the marketplace, the faster we can find our way in this
tough environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;School (or at least some form of education) is essential, but it&amp;rsquo;s not enough.
It provides the foundation, but that&amp;rsquo;s only part of the edifice. The rest is
ours to build the way we want, with our own hands, by our own personal
ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jim Rohn said, &amp;ldquo;work harder on yourself that you do on anything else.&amp;rdquo; I
believe this is especially true in school because that&amp;rsquo;s when we&amp;rsquo;re most
willing to learn — when we have the passion, the dreams, and the energy. For
most of us it only gets harder as we get older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t focus only on the technical and practical side of
things. The day I started learning about personal development, or how to
achieve success, wealth, and happiness, was one of the turning points of my
life. There are valuable lessons to learn and fundamentals to master.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If we are to climb the ladder of success, our country may help us take the
first step by providing schools that can get us our first job, but we have to
take all the other ones.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://thibaut.me/articles/richest-man-in-babylon-review/</id>
    <title>Book Review: The Richest Man in Babylon</title>
    <link href="https://thibaut.me/articles/richest-man-in-babylon-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <published>2010-02-20T19:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2010-02-20T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Thibaut</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just finished reading &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Richest-Man-Babylon-George-Clason/dp/0451205367/"&gt;The Richest Man in Babylon&lt;/a&gt;
by George Samuel Clason. It&amp;rsquo;s a short book with life-changing capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Written in the 1920s, it&amp;rsquo;s packed with parables set in ancient Babylon (the
wealthiest city of the ancient world) more than 6,000 years ago, yet its
lessons and wisdom still apply today. The laws of money are universal and
unchanging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the inspiring stories of ancient craftsmen, merchants, and money
lenders we learn how to repay debts and achieve financial success with nothing
to start with (most of these men and women started as slaves). It explains the
fundamentals of money: how to acquire it, keep it, and grow it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principles in this book are simple and one might even find them obvious,
but to be reminded of them in the way George Clason has presented them is of
great value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s said the book is &amp;ldquo;beloved by million&amp;rdquo;; I certainly liked it and would
recommend it to anyone who hasn&amp;rsquo;t read it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
